<?xml version="1.0"?>
<dictionary>
  <word>
    <name>abase</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>lower; degrade; humiliate</defn>
    <sentence>Anna expected to have to curtsy to the King of Siam; when told to cast herself down on the ground before him, however, she refused to abase herself.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abash</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>embarrass</defn>
    <sentence>He was not at all abashed by her open admiration.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>subside or moderate</defn>
    <sentence>Rather than leaving immediately, they waited for the storm to abate.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abbreviate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>shorten</defn>
    <sentence>Because we were running out of time, the lecturer had to abbreviate her speech.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abdicate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>renounce; give up</defn>
    <sentence>When Edward VIII abdicated the British throne, he surprised the entire world.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>aberrant</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>abnormal or deviant</defn>
    <sentence>Given the aberrant nature of the data, we came to doubt the validity of the entire experiment.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>aberration</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>abnormality; departure from the norm; mental irregularity or disorder</defn>
    <sentence>It remains the consensus among investors on Wall Street that current high oil prices are a temporary aberration and that we shall soon see a return to cheap oil.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abet</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>assist, usually in doing somethign wrong; encourage</defn>
    <sentence>She was unwilling to abet him in the swindle he had planned.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abeyance</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>suspended action</defn>
    <sentence>The deal was held in abeyance until her arrival.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abhor</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>detest; hate</defn>
    <sentence>She abhorred all forms of bigotry.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abject</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>wretched; lacking pride</defn>
    <sentence>On the streets of New York the homeless live in abject poverty, huddling in doorways to find shelter from the wind.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abjure</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>renounce upon oath; disavow</defn>
    <sentence>Pressure from university authorities caused the young scholar to abjure his heretical opinions.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>ablution</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>washing</defn>
    <sentence>His daily ablutions were accompanied by loud noises that he humorously labeled "Opera in the Bath."</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abnegation</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>renunciation; self-sacrifice</defn>
    <sentence>Though Rudolph and Duchess Flavia loved one another, their love was doomed, for she had to wed the king; their act of abnegation was necessary to preserve th kingdom.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abolish</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>cancel; put an end to</defn>
    <sentence>The president of the college refused to abolish the physical education requirement.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abominable</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>detestable; extremely unpleasant; very bad</defn>
    <sentence>Mary liked John until she learned he was also dating Susan; then she called him an abominable young man, with abominable taste in women.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abominate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>loathe; hate</defn>
    <sentence>Moses scolded the idol worshippers in the tribe because he abominated the custom.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>aboriginal</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>being the first of its kind in a region; primitive; native</defn>
    <sentence>Her studies of the primitive art forms of the aboriginal indians were widely reported in the scientific journals.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abortive</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>unsuccessful; fruitless</defn>
    <sentence>Attacked by armed troops, the Chinese students had to abandon their abortive attempt to democratize Beijing peacefully.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abrasive</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>rubbing away; tending to grind down</defn>
    <sentence>Just as abrasive cleaning powders can wear away a shiny finish, abrasive remarks can wear away a listener's patience.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abridge</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>condense or shorten</defn>
    <sentence>Because the publishers felt the public wanted a shorter version of War and Peace, they proceeded to abridge the novel.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abrogate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>abolish</defn>
    <sentence>The king intended to abrogate the decree issued by his predecessor.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abscission</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>removal by cutting off, as in surgery; separation</defn>
    <sentence>Gas gangrene spreads so swiftly and is so potentially deadly that doctors advise abscission of teh gangrenous tissue. When a flower or leaf separates naturally from the parent plant, this process is called abscission or leaf fall.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abscond</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>depart secretly and hide</defn>
    <sentence>The teller who absconded with the bonds went uncaptured until someone recognized him from his photograph on America's Most Wanted.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>absolute</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>complete; totally unlimited; certain</defn>
    <sentence>Although the King of Siam was an absolute monarch, he did not watn to behead his unfaithful wife without absolute evidence of her infidelity.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>absolve</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>pardon (an offense)</defn>
    <sentence>The father confessor absolved him of his sins.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abstain</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>refrain; withhold from participation</defn>
    <sentence>After considering the effect of alcohol on his athletic performance, he decided to abstain from drinking while he trained for the race.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abstemious</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>sparing in eating and drinking; temperate</defn>
    <sentence>Concerned whether her vegetarian son's abstemious diet provided him with sufficient protein, the worried mother pressed food on him.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abstinence</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>restraint from eating or drinking</defn>
    <sentence>The doctor recommended total abstinence from salted foods.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abstract</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>theoretical; not concrete; nonrepresentational</defn>
    <sentence>To him, hunger was an abstract concept; he had never missed a meal.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abstruse</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>obscure; profound; difficult to understand</defn>
    <sentence>Baffled by the abstruse philosophical texts assigned in class, Dave asked Lexy to explain Kant's Critique of Pure Reason.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abusive</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>coarsely insulting; physically harmful</defn>
    <sentence>An abusive parent damages a child both mentally and physically.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abut</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>border upon; adjoin</defn>
    <sentence>Where our estates abut, we must build a fence.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abysmal</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>bottomless</defn>
    <sentence>His arrogance is exceeded only by his abysmal ignorance.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>abyss</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>enormous chasm; vast, bottomless pit</defn>
    <sentence>Darth Vader seized the evil emperor and hurled him into the abyss.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>academic</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>related to a school; not practical or directly useful</defn>
    <sentence>The dean's talk about reforming academic policies was only an academic discussion: we knew little, if anything, would change.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accede</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>agree</defn>
    <sentence>If I accede to this demand for black-mail, I am afraid that I will be th victim of future demands.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accelerate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>move faster</defn>
    <sentence>In our science class, we learn how falling bodies accelerate.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accessible</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>easy to approach; obtainable</defn>
    <sentence>We asked our guide whether the ruins were accessible on foot.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accessory</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>additional object; useful but not essential thing</defn>
    <sentence>She bought an attractive handbag as an accessory for her dress.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acclaim</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>applaud; announce with great approval</defn>
    <sentence>The sportscasters acclaimed every American victory in the Olympics and decried every American defeat.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acclimate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>adjust to climate or environment; adapt</defn>
    <sentence>One of the difficulties of our present air age is the need of travelers to acclimate themselves to their new and often strange environments.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acclivity</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>sharp upslope of a hill</defn>
    <sentence>The car could not go up the acclivity in high gear.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accolade</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>award of merit</defn>
    <sentence>In Hollywood, an "Oscar" is the highest accolade.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accommodate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>oblige or help someone; adjust or bring into harmony; adapt</defn>
    <sentence>Mitch always did everything possible to accommodate his elderly relatives, from driving them to medical appointments to helping them with paperwork.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accomplice</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>partner in crime</defn>
    <sentence>Because he had provided the criminal with the lethal weapon, he was arrested as an accomplice in the murder.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accord</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>agreement</defn>
    <sentence>She was in complete accord with the verdict.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accost</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>approach and speak first to a person</defn>
    <sentence>When the two young men accosted me, I was frightened because I thought they were going to attack me.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accoutre</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>equip</defn>
    <sentence>The fisherman was accoutred with the best that the sporting goods store could supply.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accretion</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>growth; increase</defn>
    <sentence>Over the years Bob put on weight; because of this accretion of flesh, he went from size M to size XL.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accrue</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>come about by addition</defn>
    <sentence>You must pay the interest that has accrued on your debt as well as the principal sum.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acerbic</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>bitter or sour in nature; sharp and cutting</defn>
    <sentence>Noted for her acerbic with and gossiping.  Alice Roosevelt Longworth had a pillow in her home embroidered with the legend "If you can't say something good about someone, sit right here by me."</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acerbity</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>bitterness of speech and temper</defn>
    <sentence>The meeting of the United Nations Assembly was marked with such acerbity that observers held little hope of reaching any useful settlement of the problem.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acetic</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>vinegary</defn>
    <sentence>The salad had an exceedingly acetic flavor.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acidulous</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>slightly sour; sharp; caustic</defn>
    <sentence>James was unpopular because of his sarcastic and acidulous remarks.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acknowledge</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>recognize; admit</defn>
    <sentence>Although I acknowledge that the Beatles' tunes sounds pretty dated nowadays, I still prefer them to the gangsta rap songs my brothers play.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acme</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>peak; pinnacle; highest point</defn>
    <sentence>Welles's success in Citizen kane marked the acme of his career as an actor; never again did he achieve such popular acclaim.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acoustics</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>science of sounds; quality that makes a room easy or hard to hear in</defn>
    <sentence>Carnegie Hall is liked by music lovers because of its fine acoustics.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acquiesce</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>assent; agree passively</defn>
    <sentence>Although she appeared to acquiesce to her employer's suggestings, I could tell she had reservations about the changes he wanted made.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acquittal</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>deliverance from a charge</defn>
    <sentence>His acquittal by the jury surprised those who had thought him guilty.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acrid</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>sharp; bitterly pungent</defn>
    <sentence>The acrid odor of burnt gunpowder filled the room after the pistol had been fired.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acrimonious</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>bitter in words or manner</defn>
    <sentence>The candidate attacked his opponent in highly acrimonious temrs.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acrophobia</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>fear of heights</defn>
    <sentence>A born salesman, he could convince someone with a bad case of acrophobia to sign up for a life memberhship in a sky-diving club.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>actuarial</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>calculating; pertaining to insurance statistics</defn>
    <sentence>Accordign to recent actuarial tables, life expectancy  is greater today than it was a century ago.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>actuate</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>motivate</defn>
    <sentence>I fail to understand what actuated you to reply to this letter so nastily.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>accumen</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>mental keenness</defn>
    <sentence>Her business acumen helped her to succeed where others had failed.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>acute</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>quickly perceptive; keen; brief and severe</defn>
    <sentence>The acute young doctor realized immediately that the gradual deterioration of her patient's once-acute hearing was due to a chronic illness, not an acute one.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adage</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>wise saying; proverb</defn>
    <sentence>There is much truth in the old adage aobout fools and their money.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adamant</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>hard; inflexible</defn>
    <sentence>In this movie Bronson played the part of a revenge-driven man, adamant in his determination to punish the criminals who destroyed his family.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adapt</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>alter; modify</defn>
    <sentence>Some species of animals have become extinct because they could not adapt to a changing environment.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>addendum</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>addition; appendix to book</defn>
    <sentence>Jane's editor approved her new comparative literature text but thought it would be even better with an addendum on recent developments in literary crticism.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>addiction</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>compulsive, habitual need</defn>
    <sentence>His addiction to drugs caused his friends much grief.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>addle</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>muddle; drive crazy; become rotten</defn>
    <sentence>This idiotic plan is confusing enough to addle anyone.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>address</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>direct a speech to; deal with or discuss</defn>
    <sentence>Due to address the convention in July, Brown planned to address the issue of low-income housing in his speech.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adept</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>expert at</defn>
    <sentence>She was adept at the fine art of irritating people.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adhere</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>stick fast</defn>
    <sentence>I will adhere to this opinion until proof that I am wrong is presented.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adherent</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>supporter; follower</defn>
    <sentence>In the wake of the scandal, the senator's one-time adherents quietly deserted him.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adjacent</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>adjoining; neighboring; close by</defn>
    <sentence>Philip's best friend Jason lived only four houses down the block, near but not immediately adjacent.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adjunct</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>something (generally nonessential or inferior) added on or attached</defn>
    <sentence>Although I don't absolutely need a second computer, I plan to buy a laptop to serve as an adjunct to my desktop model.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adjuration</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>solemn urging</defn>
    <sentence>Her adjuration to tell the truth did not change the witnesses' testimony.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adjutant</name>
    <pos>n</pos>
    <defn>staff officer assisting the commander; assistant</defn>
    <sentence>Though Wellington delegated many tasks to his chief adjutant, Lord Fitzroy Somerset, Somerset was in no doubt as to who made all major decisions.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>admonish</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>warn; reprove</defn>
    <sentence>When her courtiers questioned her religious beliefs, Mary Stuart admonished them, declaring that she would worship as she pleased.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adorn</name>
    <pos>v</pos>
    <defn>decorate</defn>
    <sentence>Wall paintings and carved statues adorned the temple.</sentence>
  </word>
  <word>
    <name>adroit</name>
    <pos>adj</pos>
    <defn>skillful</defn>
    <sentence>Her adroit handling of the delicate situation pleased her employers.</sentence>
  </word>
</dictionary>
